# 大家好 今天來兄弟家這個蘭花基地看一下
Hi everyone! Today we come to our buddy's orchid cultivation site and have a look.
# 他家種了好這個蘭花
He has planted a lot of orchids.
# 那甚麼品種
Whichever species...
# 你看 都有 七八十種品種哦
Look! He has everything. There are up to eighty species.
# 進去看一下
Let's take a look inside.
# 你看 這個
Look! This one,
# 這個也很漂亮哦
this one is really pretty, isn't it?
# 它這個
It's like,
# 就這樣直接種下去就可以啦
it can be planted right away.
# 它這 這個要到冬天
It's ah, in winter,
# 冬天 冬天過年時候才會開花
winter, it won't blossom until winter, when the Chinese New Year comes.
# 好多工人都在這裡面
A lot of workers are over there inside.
# 上班
They're working.
# 沒 這個沒甚麼味道 但
No, it doesn't smell anything now. But,
# 等下它開了花之後就
later, when it blossoms,
# 那個味道就很濃啦
the fragrance will become really significant.
# 我聽那個 那個技術員說這個開的花 那個
The, you know, the technician over there told me that the flowers are, like,
# 很香的哦
the flowers smell really nice.
# 就跟我們山上的野蘭花差不多
It's almost the same as the wild orchids on our hill.
# 看上去就是 但是品種下一樣的
They look alike. But they're of different species.
# 帶動了好多就業
It brings a lot of job opportunities.
# 小石頭跟那個花去瞉
Small rocks and peanut shell,
# 拌在一起
mixed together,
# 就可以種啦
makes perfect soil for the orchids.
# 你看 這個大片都是
Look! The site covers the whole area here.
# 一片綠油油的
It's green everywhere.
# 你看 聽那個技術員說
Look! The technician told me,
# 他說這個
he told me that,
# 這個是它爸爸 這個 老一點的就叫它爸爸
This is its daddy. This one, the older one is called the daddy.
# 不是哦 它爺爺哦
Ah no, it's the grandpa.
# 搞錯啦 這是它爺爺
I mixed them up. This is the grandpa.
# 這是它老爸
And this is the daddy.
# 這種 這種剛長出來的就是它孫子
This one, the one that has just grown out, is the grandson.
# 剛好就是一定人
So the whole family is here.
# 剛好住在一個窩里面
They're living under the same roof.
# 等下開 開蘭花的時候就很香
It will, it will smell really nice later when the orchids blossom.
# 這個時候還下香
You can't smell anything at this moment.
# 種植起來好簡單哦
Planting it is a piece of cake.
# 就用小石頭
Simply take some small rocks,
# 跟那個頭瞉之類的
together with some bean shells or whatever,
# 放下去就可以啦
plant it in, that's it.
# 換個盆 換個竹筒的話也可以喲
Using another pot, I mean a bamboo tube, is also fine.
# 但竹同太小啦
But a bamboo tube might be too small.
# 要大竹子才行
You may need a big bamboo.
# 把它放回去
Let me put it back.
# 你看
Look!
# 這個 這個叫墨蘭
This is, this is called "ink orchid".
# 黑黑的 叫墨蘭
The colour is dark. So it's called "ink orchid".
# 它的這個 綠色綠到 綠到那種發黑的那種
It's in fact green, dark green, so dark that it's almost, sort of like, black.
# 很靚
Beautiful
# 還沒開花 開花了更靚
It has not yet blossomed. It will be even more beautiful when it blossoms.
# 你看 這個就漂亮啦 你看
Look! It's really pretty, isn't it?
# 開了一朵花出來
One flower has already blossomed.
# 它開了好多朵 都被凋謝啦 (註︰被凋謝....)
There should have been a lot of flowers. But most have already withered.
# 剩下這一朵
Only this one remains.
# 好靚哦
It's so beautiful!
# 它這個花
The flower is,
# 淡淡的 淡淡的紫色
is in light, light violet.
# 好多株哇 這裡
Here's not one, but many of them.
# 都是滿盆的
The pot is completely filled.
# 差不多它們肯定要分 分盆啦
I'm sure that they will need to be sep, separated very soon.
# 這些太滿啦
There are no more rooms at all.
# 你看 這也開了一朵花
Look! Here's another flower.
# 這花很不錯哦
This flower is really not bad.
# 很靚
Beautiful!
# 放在這裡先
Put it here first.
# 看一下其它的
And have a look at the others.
# 你看 這是自動噴水的哦
Look! An automatic watering system is installed here.
# 隨便噴一下就濕掉啦
The whole site get drenched in no time.
# 好均勻啊 噴的
It's really efficient, you know.
# 噴了5分鐘就足夠了哦
I bet five minutes would be all it needs, right?
# 一般要噴10分鐘
Normally it takes ten minutes.
# 要噴10分鐘
Ten minutes, I see.
# 嗯 噴了就是噴透來
Um! The whole site needs to be thoroughly watered.
# 你看 給它們洗了一個澡
Look! They've now taken a shower.
# 變漂亮了哦
And they become so pretty now.
# 噴了幾分鐘
It has taken a few minutes.
# 哇 你看 那個
Wa! Look! These are,
# 雜交
hybrid.
# 台北小姐
"Ms Taipei"
# 它還那麼小 還不會開花
They're still that small. They are not going to blossom now.
# 要長大啦 它就會開花啦
They will blossom once they grow up.
# 一棵變十棵
One plant will become ten.
# 可以喲
Not bad!
# (非對白)
Hybrid Orchid "Ms Taipei"
Cymbidium, Orchidaceae, originated in Taipei, China. Suitable for tropical/subtropical climate. Hybridized in Taiwan.
# (非對白)
Flowers are big and plenty, with pink or red strips, subtle fragrance. Stems can reach above 70 cm. Up to a dozen of flowers on each stem.
# 你看 這個
Look! This one,
# 這個開花了哦 這個
this one has already blossomed, you know.
# 它 我聽我兄弟說 他現在把花全部剪掉啦
It's ah, my buddy told me that all flowers are to be cut away at the present moment,
# 不讓它開花
to make sure that no flowers are here now.
# 你看 這個 含花待放
Look! This bud, is almost ready to blossom.
# 現在肯定是
I'm sure that,
# 躲過來兄弟的剪刀
it has escaped from my buddy's scissors.
# 不然都會被剪掉的
It would have already been cut away otherwise.
# 哎呀 好香啊
Aya! It smells so good!
# 水困的香味一樣
It's like the fragrance of fruits.
# 這個好漂亮
It's really pretty.
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 把這棵帶回去
I'll take this one home.